<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Tangamandapio (Publicaciones sobre zeppelin)</title><link>http://elopio.net/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://elopio.net/es/categories/zeppelin.xml"></atom:link><language>es</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 17:12:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Follow this quality checklist before an audit</title><link>http://elopio.net/es/blog/quality-checklist-before-audit/</link><dc:creator>Leo Arias</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.com/"&gt;OpenZeppelin&lt;/a&gt; we help protect the core
infrastructure of open and decentralized applications. I'm part of the Research
team, which is in charge of conducting
&lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.com/security-audits/"&gt;security audits&lt;/a&gt;.
We review tons of lines of code written by very smart developers for projects
that will shake the foundations of our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding security vulnerabilities in this futuristic cypherpunk environment is
super challenging and fun, but
&lt;a href="https://blog.openzeppelin.com/"&gt;we have already covered those topics elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.
I think that security actually starts in a
pretty boring and traditional place, full of the wisdom that our elders have
collected through millennia of developing software in community. Standing on
their shoulders, I want to share our checklist for basic quality measures
that your next awesome project should consider before you hand it over for an
external audit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Choose a free software license&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closed code is inherently insecure. If people who use your project can't inspect it,
study it, hack it, and experiment on it, there's no way it can be trusted. If you
hold abusive control over your users, nothing prevents you (or anyone
more powerful than you) from making them vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html"&gt;Free Software Definition&lt;/a&gt;,
and begin with &lt;a href="https://choosealicense.com/"&gt;choosing the license&lt;/a&gt; that best
suits your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: previously we introduced here Richard Stallman as a wise elder, dressed as a saint 🤦. 
This joke no longer seems appropriate due to his repeated 
bad comments, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman#Controversy_and_resignation_from_MIT_and_Free_Software_Foundation"&gt;brought to light by a recent controversy&lt;/a&gt;.
Let's just say that we thank him for having hacked copyright laws, for starting the free software movement, and 
for writing the above definition. And that we consider appropriate him stepping down from his
leadership position in the free software community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Build your core team of maintainers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your project succeeds, hundreds of external contributors will surely be supporting it. But in order to
get to that point, you'll need to bootstrap with a strong and diverse team of core
maintainers. They'll take care of the bulk of the work, the fun and the boring
parts, proposing and reviewing the code of your shared project. Together,
you all need to have strong knowledge of all points on this checklist.
Look not only for technical knowledge, but also for a knack for cat-herding and a
healthy work style—because, well, things will get complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay attention to your &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor"&gt;bus factor&lt;/a&gt;:
make sure your team members are sharing their expertise, the lessons learned, and their
responsibilities, while at the same time constantly mentoring new people
that could potentially join the core team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And somebody will have to lead and orchestrate in order to get value out of the eternal
tendency toward chaos. Let me introduce you to the magician,
&lt;a href="http://www.camilletalk.com/"&gt;Camille Fournier&lt;/a&gt;, who wrote THE book on technical
management,
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/33369254-the-manager-s-path"&gt;The Manager's Path&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.camilletalk.com/contact/"&gt;&lt;img src="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/56bf8b0622482edc3dc1919d/t/56bf8ef5f85082335f63196b/1455400011874/21793992240_b56cd4b3e2_o+%281%29.jpg?format=500w" alt="Camille Fournier" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camille Fournier (Image taken from
&lt;a href="http://www.camilletalk.com/contact/"&gt;her website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Write clean code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.osnews.com/story/19266/wtfsm/"&gt;The only valid measurement of code quality is WTFs per minute&lt;/a&gt;. This point &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be simple. If things get overly complicated or
weird, you're doing it wrong. Go for a walk and try again with fresh eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don't get me wrong: no interesting software project is simple. Add the
complexity dimensions of decentralization, transparency, cryptography, and all
these shiny ideas that are keeping us so busy these days. It's complicated by
design. But with the correct abstractions, a well thought-out model, and proper encapsulation,
you can start building the bank-killer app one line at a time. And each of
those lines &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be clean and readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not a spectacular programmer, I was just lucky to find Uncle Bob
Martin's book
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3735293-clean-code"&gt;Clean Code&lt;/a&gt; at
the right moment and to have read a never-ending stream of very, very ugly code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_C._Martin#/media/File:Robert_Cecil_Martin.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ee/Robert_Cecil_Martin.png/800px-Robert_Cecil_Martin.png" alt="Robert C. Martin" height="250"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Cecil Martin (Image taken from
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_C._Martin#/media/File:Robert_Cecil_Martin.png"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all core maintainers reach common ground on this topic, you should
enforce a consistent code style by running a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lint_(software)"&gt;linter&lt;/a&gt; on every new line of
code that's added. The particular rules aren't as important as
following them strictly is, but if you can
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/openzeppelin-solidity/issues/1396#issuecomment-440426310"&gt;sacrifice your peculiar preferences to be consistent with the rest of the world&lt;/a&gt;, your contributors will appreciate it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also practice slow-food... er, slow programming.
Take your time, enjoy the journey to mastering this craft, and when you've built something you can
proudly set free, let the masses read it and judge it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Write unit tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write unit tests. Tons of them. 100% coverage. This might sound extreme, but hey, your code is now
playing directly with somebody else's money. If you forget, or just get lazy and
don't write a test for that super obvious line of code, you might be leaving an open
door for an exploit later in the game that will make your project crash, and
all this magic internet money will disappear in no time. It &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel immediately more secure when I do test-driven development. At least give
an honest try to writing the tests first, and get into a cycle of
red-green-refactor. There are other techniques that can achieve the same
result, but I suggest starting there and then deviating if you find good
reasons to do so. Never worked this way? Read
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/387190.Test_Driven_Development"&gt;Test Driven Development: By Example&lt;/a&gt;
by Kent Beck. It's a quick read that will help you avoid the temptation of
just jumping into code without thinking it through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, even if you design for testability, you'll find many scenarios that are
hard to test. Gerard Meszaros provides all the answers in
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/337302.xUnit_Test_Patterns"&gt;xUnit Test Patterns&lt;/a&gt;.
This book is huge, so I recommend choosing a designated test expert on your
team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent_Beck#/media/File:Kent_Beck_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c0/Kent_Beck_1.jpg" alt="Kent Beck" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gerardmes"&gt;&lt;img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/71233259/Gerard_in_Vancouver__Brian_Foote-O-O_Canada_012_.jpg" alt="Gerard Meszaros" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left: Kent Beck speaking in 2001 (Image taken from
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent_Beck#/media/File:Kent_Beck_1.jpg"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)
Right: Gerard Meszaros (Image taken from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gerardmes"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, make sure to run your unit tests on every single pull request, and make sure
they're &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; green before merging the changes. In addition, you can set up a
test coverage report to ensure that test coverage never goes down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Test early, test often, test agile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have your first layer of tests covered with tons of unit tests,
what comes next is...more tests! You need to test the integration between
all of your components, then go one level higher to test your
application from the point of view of a real user, and then go even
higher to test the interactions with other systems end-to-end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this is the biggest challenge, and designing a good process that
keeps many bugs out of your system can be as difficult as designing the system
itself. Iterate, automate as much as possible, share the load of manual
testing...and let your community help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll talk later about community, but I think this is the reason for
publishing your code as early as possible: you can get help from early adopters
and enthusiasts to validate your system, not only for correctness but also to
verify that you're focusing on the right user stories and that you're tackling a
real problem with a user-friendly solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has been written about iterative development processes that deliver
functionalities in progressive sprints and milestones. I found Mike Cohn's
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6707987-succeeding-with-agile"&gt;Succeeding with Agile: Software Development Using Scrum&lt;/a&gt;
a good place to start, but keep in mind that any methodology will have to be
adjusted to your team, your users, and your context. There are a lot fewer
resources focused on the quality and testing part; that's why I was so happy
when I read
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/5341009-agile-testing"&gt;Agile Testing&lt;/a&gt; by
Lisa Crispin and Janet Gregory, which is full of good ideas and advice. But
let me stress again: nothing you read will perfectly fit your project, so take your
time to design the testing process with as much love and care as you use when
designing the system's architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Cohn#/media/File:Mike_Cohn_2013-06-12.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/37/Mike_Cohn_2013-06-12.jpg/1280px-Mike_Cohn_2013-06-12.jpg" alt="Mike Cohn" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://agiletester.ca/about-the-authors/"&gt;&lt;img src="https://agiletester.ca/wp-content/uploads/sites/26/2013/09/Lisa-Crispin-and-Janet-Gregory.jpg" alt="Lisa Crispin and Janet Gregory" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left: Mike Cohn in 2013 (Image taken from
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Cohn#/media/File:Mike_Cohn_2013-06-12.jpg"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)
Right: Right: Lisa Crispin and Janet Gregory (Image taken from their
&lt;a href="https://agiletester.ca/about-the-authors/"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there's still some debate about the perfect moment for auditing a project (i.e, before or after the code is
published), I think audits should be performed when there's a release candidate
ready to be deployed to mainnet, after you have performed extensive alpha and
beta testing. I see room for auditing before the code has been published,
but in this case, the audit would be more related to checking that the development
process will lead to a high-quality, properly tested release candidate and
validating the bases of your project than to performing a deep and thorough
inspection of the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this doesn’t mean that you have to wait until the end of a long
development phase to prepare for a release and audit. Once you start writing and
testing clean code in incremental iterations, it becomes easier to think about
your complex system. Many smaller independent parts will start to pop up, which
can be extracted, generalized, and packaged for reuse, reducing anxiety for
developers and auditors. These packages are the focus of
&lt;a href="https://zeppelinos.org/"&gt;ZeppelinOS&lt;/a&gt; for this year, to know more take a look at
the &lt;a href="https://blog.zeppelinos.org/state-of-evm-packages-end-of-2018/"&gt;State of EVM Packages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Write documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my least favorite part, by far. So let's keep it simple, starting at
the beginning: the README, the most important file of your repository.
And yet, it's usually either empty or bloated, outdated, and ugly. Ideally, as it's the
first thing developers and potential contributors will read, it should work as a clear, straightforward index of
your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's best not to get creative here. Just follow this simple specification that
works for all cases, proposed by Richard Littauer in
&lt;a href="https://github.com/RichardLitt/standard-readme/blob/master/spec.md"&gt;Standard Readme&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Do not forget&lt;/em&gt; to include a specific section in the main README that states how people should disclose any security
vulnerabilities found in your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/richlitt"&gt;&lt;img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/853672023511490561/m_RAvJfy.jpg" alt="Richard Littauer" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Littauer (Image taken from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/richlitt"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next come the docstrings, the documentation inside your code files. We hit
an apparent conflict here, since in theory, if your code is clean,
it will not require documentation. However, note that we are no longer
designing standalone systems that work as a black box. We are building
protocols for decentralized applications, and your code will be called by all sorts
of external agents. So by all means, document every function that's part
of the contract's public API, following the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ethereum/wiki/wiki/Ethereum-Natural-Specification-Format"&gt;NatSpec format&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the next point. I highly recommend that you document the
specification of your protocol—that's how others will know what to call and
what to expect. But more related to the topic at hand, in an audit, we check that
the implemented code works as intended by the specification. That's why this
document is a &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt;: without it, auditors will just guess at your intentions, which
might result in some issues getting missed because they're completely consistent
within the system but take it to a state that you want to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there's the user documentation. For high-quality systems,
writing the user documentation should be mostly painless. The moment things get cumbersome
while documenting, consider re-evaluating your user stories, and don't be afraid to go back to iterate on
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Check your dependencies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your project builds on top of many, many others. It will probably depend at least
on the Ethereum protocol and its network of nodes, and on Solidity, a bunch of
Ethereum Improvement Proposals and their implementation, libraries for testing and UI, and maybe hundreds
of other small projects. Even if yours is secure, you need to check how healthy your dependencies are,
since they can easily become the source of
vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I mentioned that your team should have strong and diverse knowledge.
That includes knowledge of all the projects that surround you. You should be able to
write idiomatic code following the best practices of the language, to identify
and avoid known issues, always keeping an eye on new
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Vulnerabilities_and_Exposures"&gt;CVEs&lt;/a&gt;
that may directly (or indirectly, through third-party dependencies) affect your project. Moreover, try to participate in the communities around your
dependencies, as it's an excellent way to see firsthand how safe and trustworthy they are.
You should also consider &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; participating in those communities, to gain some karma that will surely come in
handy later when you need new features and bug fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, don't forget to pay attention to your dependencies' finances. When making your project's budget,
take into account a share for your dependencies, as they may need it in order
to remain actively maintained. There's a very nice project called
&lt;a href="https://opencollective.com/discover"&gt;OpenCollective&lt;/a&gt;,
led by Pia Mancini, which is making it extremely easy to transparently support
the organizations and developers you depend on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.piamancini.com/"&gt;&lt;img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a7bdaa_ab650ff17e804731b7cf560bc5ee9a02~mv2.jpg/v1/crop/x_0,y_120,w_961,h_961/fill/w_530,h_530,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01/Pia%20Mancini%20-%20headshot.jpg" alt="Pia Mancini" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pia Mancini (Image taken from her &lt;a href="https://www.piamancini.com/"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, with &lt;a href="https://zeppelinos.org/"&gt;ZeppelinOS&lt;/a&gt;, we're building a
platform that will let you vouch for the security of a package. It's in beta
testing, so expect exciting news very soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specific to Ethereum and Solidity, the community is collecting the lessons
learned (usually in a painful way). You can learn a lot about interesting
and tricky vulnerabilities playing the
&lt;a href="https://ethernaut.zeppelin.solutions/"&gt;Ethernaut capture-the-flag game&lt;/a&gt;.
We've
&lt;a href="https://blog.zeppelin.solutions/tagged/security"&gt;published many of our past audits&lt;/a&gt;
with descriptions of the issues found, recommendations, and usually a link
to the patch that fixes them. All of our learnings from audits are distilled into
the &lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.org/"&gt;OpenZeppelin package&lt;/a&gt;, which you should definitely add
to your list of dependencies—if you're not one of the thousands that already did. The
&lt;a href="https://smartcontractsecurity.github.io/SWC-registry/"&gt;Smart Contracts Weakness Registry&lt;/a&gt;
maintained by the Mythril team is also a great resource for learning from the
experience of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever approach you take, remember that as the Ethereum space is very young and unexplored, we're learning many things as we go, so &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt;
proceed with caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;✔️ Build your community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a complement to the first point: code without a community is insecure.
The community gives you eyes to monitor the project, hands to test it in a
real environment, support to survive challenging problems, and resilience to
adjust to the unexpected. No amount of money, experience, or knowledge
can substitute for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you publish the code, you can get started engaging your community. If your
project is interesting, they will come, and this is where the cat-herding
abilities of your team will shine. However, you definitely need to set up proper and fluent communication channels,
invest in some marketing, and hire a bold community manager with a plan to disentangle
and wisely leverage all the opportunities your community brings. I can't
recommend highly enough the writings and videos by
&lt;a href="https://www.jonobacon.com/"&gt;Jono Bacon&lt;/a&gt;, who has covered all the topics you
can imagine about community management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonobacon/12622356185/"&gt;&lt;img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3740/12622356185_b89d134675_k.jpg" alt="Jono Bacon" height="350"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jono Bacon in 2014 (Image taken from &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonobacon/12622356185/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be thoughtful and caring with your community. A small step that
goes a long way is to adopt and enforce a
&lt;a href="https://www.contributor-covenant.org/"&gt;code of conduct&lt;/a&gt; so you can all feel
safe. Then, write some contribution guidelines to make sure that all of their
enthusiasm can be put to good use and they don't get lost. Lastly, think about
setting up a &lt;a href="https://www.hackerone.com/"&gt;bug bounty program&lt;/a&gt; that will
encourage your community to watch out for vulnerabilities in the wild,
providing hackers with enough incentives to disclose security issues in a responsible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tldr:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅ Choose a free software license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅ Build a strong and diverse team of core maintainers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Increase your bus factor: share knowledge and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅ Choose a good leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Write clean code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Enforce a consistent code style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Ensure 100% unit test coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Enforce green tests on all your pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Design your iterative development and testing process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Publish your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Write a good README.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Document the functions of your public API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Document your protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Write the end-user documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Make sure that your dependencies can be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Review known issues and keep an eye out for new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Use OpenZeppelin, the community-vetted standard for smart contract development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅️ Build and care for your community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ready to hire an auditing team?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's us! :) The OpenZeppelin team can help you assess the quality of your project and
processes. We'll take a deep and thorough dive into your code, with years of experience hacking,
researching, and developing on blockchains, plus a little touch of Latin
American fire, to give you and your users all the confidence you need to
continue building the core systems of this new decentralized, global, and open economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're available for auditing services, so check out this information about
&lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.com/security-audits/"&gt;security audits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://notonlyowner.com/"&gt;Martín Abbatemarco&lt;/a&gt; for editing this
post, to the OpenZeppelin team for the continuous experimentation and feedback,
and to &lt;a href="https://blog.openzeppelin.com/tagged/security"&gt;our customers&lt;/a&gt; for
trusting us and helping us better understand what makes a free software
project awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be part of our community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue the discussion on our &lt;a href="https://forum.openzeppelin.com/"&gt;forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Request a &lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.com/security-audits/"&gt;security audit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even better, &lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.com/jobs/"&gt;join the team&lt;/a&gt; 🚀&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://elopio.net/es/blog/quality-checklist-before-audit/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 15:58:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On crowdsales and multiple inheritance</title><link>http://elopio.net/es/blog/crowdsales-and-multiple-inheritance/</link><dc:creator>Leo Arias</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On 2017 we saw a mind-blowing number of crowdsales and ICOs running in the
Ethereum blockchain. They have proven to be a
powerful tool to collect the funds required to start a project, and they are
one of the most common uses for smart contracts right now. The Zeppelin team
has been very involved in this topic,
&lt;a href="https://blog.zeppelin.solutions/tagged/audit"&gt;auditing many crowdsale contracts&lt;/a&gt;,
and supporting &lt;a href="https://openzeppelin.org/"&gt;OpenZeppelin&lt;/a&gt;, the most popular
framework to build these crowdsales. What we found was a lot of contracts
repeating the same basic concepts, with very similar code, and common
vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, part of the team took the task to redesign our base
&lt;code&gt;Crowdsale&lt;/code&gt; contract in order to support a lot of new crowdsale flavors out of
the box and to make the experience of building and publishing your own
crowdsale more clear and secure. The idea is to make audits less necessary,
with an architecture that is modular, that encourages reuse and that will be
collectively reviewed. These new contracts were added to OpenZeppelin version
&lt;code&gt;1.7.0&lt;/code&gt;, and since the release they have been widely used by our community with
 great success. So, this is a good moment to show off :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with a dive into
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/crowdsale/Crowdsale.sol"&gt;the source code of the &lt;code&gt;Crowdsale&lt;/code&gt; base contract&lt;/a&gt;.
The first thing you will notice is a lot of comments, guiding you through the
details of the OpenZeppelin crowdsale architecture. They explain that some
functions are the core of the architecture and should not be overriden, like
&lt;code&gt;buyTokens&lt;/code&gt;. Some others like &lt;code&gt;_preValidatePurchase&lt;/code&gt; can be overriden to
implement the requirements of your crowdsale, but that extra behavior should
be concatenated with the one of the parent by calling &lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt;, to preserve the
validations from the  base contract. Some functions like
&lt;code&gt;_postValidatePurchase&lt;/code&gt; can be just added as hooks in other parts of the
crowdsale's lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on top of this base, we now provide some contracts for common
crowdsale scenarios involving
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/tree/master/contracts/crowdsale/distribution"&gt;distribution&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/tree/master/contracts/crowdsale/emission"&gt;emission&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/tree/master/contracts/crowdsale/price"&gt;price&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/tree/master/contracts/crowdsale/validation"&gt;validation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's say that you want to set a goal for your crowdsale and if it's not
met by the time the sale finishes, you want to refund all your investors. For
that, you can use the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/crowdsale/distribution/RefundableCrowdsale.sol"&gt;RefundableCrowdsale contract&lt;/a&gt;,
which overrides the base &lt;code&gt;_forwardFunds&lt;/code&gt; behavior to send the funds to a fancy
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/crowdsale/distribution/utils/RefundVault.sol"&gt;RefundVault&lt;/a&gt;
while the crowdsale is in progress, instead of sending them directly to the
wallet of the crowdsale owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common scenario is when you want the tokens to be minted when they are
purchased. For that, take a look at the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/crowdsale/emission/MintedCrowdsale.sol"&gt;MintedCrowdsale contract&lt;/a&gt;,
which overrides the simple &lt;code&gt;_deliverTokens&lt;/code&gt; behavior of the base class to call
instead the &lt;code&gt;mint&lt;/code&gt; function of an
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/token/ERC20/MintableToken.sol"&gt;ERC20 Mintable token&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we want to do something more interesting with the price of the tokens?
The base &lt;code&gt;Crowdsale&lt;/code&gt; contract defines a constant rate between tokens and wei,
but if we override &lt;code&gt;_getTokenAmount&lt;/code&gt;, we could do something like increasing
the price as the closing time of the crowdsale approaches. That's exactly what
the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/crowdsale/price/IncreasingPriceCrowdsale.sol"&gt;IncreasingPriceCrowdsale contract&lt;/a&gt;
does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started developing and deploying a crowdsale using the OpenZeppelin
framework, Gustavo Guimaraes published a nice
&lt;a href="https://blog.zeppelin.solutions/how-to-create-token-and-initial-coin-offering-contracts-using-truffle-openzeppelin-1b7a5dae99b6"&gt;guide where you will see in action a crowdsale that is timed &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; minted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just a few examples. I invite you to explore the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/tree/master/contracts/crowdsale"&gt;OpenZeppelin crowdsale contracts&lt;/a&gt;
to see all the new flavors that you can easily use to fund your cool idea;
and take a look at the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/contracts/examples/SampleCrowdsale.sol"&gt;SampleCrowdsale contract&lt;/a&gt;,
a more complex scenario that comes with full
&lt;a href="https://github.com/OpenZeppelin/zeppelin-solidity/blob/master/test/examples/SampleCrowdsale.test.js"&gt;test coverage&lt;/a&gt;.
If you like OpenZeppelin, remember that you are welcome into
&lt;a href="https://slack.openzeppelin.org/"&gt;our vibrating community&lt;/a&gt; to help us adding new
contracts or improving the existing ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the repo you will also find that all these contracts are very well tested. And
as we have seen, the new architecture is clearer and safer, with each contract
explaining the functions that you can or can't override, and how to do it.
However, you should be extra careful when combining them. It's not the same to
have three contracts with one condition than to have one contract with three
conditions. The combination increases the attack surface, so you need to have
a good idea of what you want to achieve, and know the implementation details of
the tools you are using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you go ahead and deploy a complex crowdsale that combines some of our
contracts, I would like to spend some time going deep into how Solidity works
when you combine contracts through multiple inheritance, like Gustavo did in
his guide to make a contract that inherits from &lt;code&gt;TimedCrowdsale&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; from
&lt;code&gt;MintedCrowdsale&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple inheritance is hard, and it can get very confusing if you abuse it.
Some languages don't support it at all; but it is becoming a very common
pattern on Solidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, from the point of view of the programmer, is to understand the
order of the calls when a contract has multiple parents. Let's say we have a
base contract &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;, with a function named &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;contract A {&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;  function f() {&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;    somethingA();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;  }&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we have two contracts &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;, both inherit from &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; and override &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;B&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;somethingB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;somethingC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And finaly we have a contract &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt;, which inherits from &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;, and
overrides &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt; too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;contract D is B, C {&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;  function f() {&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;    somethingD();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;    super.f();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;  }&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What happens when you call &lt;code&gt;D.f&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is called the diamond problem, because we end up with a diamond-shaped
inheritance diagram:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/8e/Diamond_inheritance.svg/180px-Diamond_inheritance.svg.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Diamond inheritance problem" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/8e/Diamond_inheritance.svg/180px-Diamond_inheritance.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(the image is from wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve it, Solidity uses C3 linearization, also called Method Resolution
Order (MRO). This means that it will linearize the inheritance graph. If &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt;
is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;contract D is B, C {}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;then &lt;code&gt;D.f&lt;/code&gt; will call:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingD();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingC();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingB();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingA();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; inherits from &lt;code&gt;B, C&lt;/code&gt;, the linearization results in D→ C→ B→ A. This
means that &lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; calls &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;. And you might be a little surprised by the
fact that calling &lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; will result on a call to &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;,
even though &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; doesn't inherit from &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, &lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; will call
&lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; is instead defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;contract D is C, B {}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;then &lt;code&gt;D.f&lt;/code&gt; will call:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingD();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingB();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingC();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;somethingA();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; inherits from &lt;code&gt;C, B&lt;/code&gt;, the linearization results in D→ B→ C→ A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice here that the order in which you declare the parent contracts matters a
lot. If the inheritance graph is not too complex, it will be easy to see that
the order of calls will follow the order in which the parents were declared,
right to left. If your inheritance is more complicated than this and the
hierarchy is not very clear, you should probably stop using multiple
inheritance and look for an alternate solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend you to read the wikipedia pages of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_inheritance"&gt;Multiple inheritance&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C3_linearization"&gt;C3 linearization&lt;/a&gt;, and the
&lt;a href="https://solidity.readthedocs.io/en/latest/contracts.html#multiple-inheritance-and-linearization"&gt;Solidity docs about multiple inheritance&lt;/a&gt;.
You will find in there a complete explanation of the C3 algorithm, and an
example with a more complicated inheritance graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better understand how this can impact your crowdsales, take a look at the
case that Philip Daian brilliantly explains on his blog post
&lt;a href="https://pdaian.com/blog/solidity-anti-patterns-fun-with-inheritance-dag-abuse/"&gt;Solidity anti-patterns: Fun with inheritance DAG abuse&lt;/a&gt;.
There, he presents a Crowdsale contract that needs "to have a whitelist
pool of preferred investors able to buy in the pre-sale [...], along with a
hard cap of the number of [...] tokens that can be distributed." On his first
(deliberately) faulty implementation, he ends up with a crowdsale that checks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;((withinPeriod &amp;amp;&amp;amp; nonZeroPurchase) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; withinCap) || (whitelist[msg.sender] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !hasEnded())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pay close attention to the resulting condition, and notice that if a
whitelisted investor buys tokens before the crowdsale has ended, she will be
able to bypass the hard cap, and buy as many tokens as she wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By just inverting the order on which the parents are defined, he fixes the
contract which will now check for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;(withinPeriod &amp;amp;&amp;amp; nonZeroPurchase || (whitelist[msg.sender] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !hasEnded())) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; withinCap&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, if the purchase attempt goes above the cap, the transaction will be
reverted even if the sender is whitelisted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some simple cases, where the order of the conditions is not
important. By now, you should have started to suspect that the contract above
became complicated because of the &lt;code&gt;||&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;) condition. Things are a lot easier
when all our conditions are merged with &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;), because in that case the
order of the conditions doesn't alter the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our new architecture was crafted for using &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; instead of returning
booleans, which works nicely to combine &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; conditions, and to revert the
transaction when one fails. Let's say that we have a crowdsale that should
&lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; allow whitelisted investors to buy tokens while the sale is open
&lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; the cap has not been reached. In this
case, the condition to check would be (in pseudocode):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;require(hasStarted() &amp;amp;&amp;amp; !hasEnded())&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;require(isInWhiteList(msg.sender))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;require(isWithinCap(msg.value))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our contract would be as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pragma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;solidity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"zeppelin-solidity/contracts/crowdsale/validation/TimedCrowdsale.sol"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"zeppelin-solidity/contracts/crowdsale/validation/WhitelistedCrowdsale.sol"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"zeppelin-solidity/contracts/crowdsale/validation/CappedCrowdsale.sol"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;WhitelistedTimedCappedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;TimedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;WhitelistedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;CappedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;WhitelistedTimedCappedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;uint256&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_rate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;address&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_wallet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;ERC20&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_token&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;uint256&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_openingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;uint256&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_closingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;uint256&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_cap&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;public&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Crowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_rate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_wallet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_token&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;TimedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_openingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_closingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;CappedCrowdsale&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_cap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter how you order the parents, all the conditions will be
checked always. But take this with a grain of salt. All the conditions will be
checked, but the order will be different. This can have different side-effects
on Solidity, as some paths will execute statements that other paths won't, and
it could lead an attacker to find a specific path that is vulnerable. Also, if
your parent contracts are not super clear, they might be hiding an &lt;code&gt;||&lt;/code&gt;
condition in a few hard-to-read code statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very easy to think that the parent contracts will just be magically merged
into something that will make sense for our use case, or to make a mistake when
we linearize them in our mind. Every use case will be different, so our
framework can't save you from the work of organizing your contracts' hierarchy.
You must analyze the linearization of the inheritance graph to get a clear view
of the functions that will be called and their order, and always always add a
full suite of automated tests for your final crowdsale contract to make sure
that it enforces all the conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish, I wanted to show you my repo where I will be doing
experiments with crowdsales and their tests:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/elopio/zeppelin-crowdsales"&gt;https://github.com/elopio/zeppelin-crowdsales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/elopio/zeppelin-crowdsales/blob/master/contracts/PreSaleWithCapCrowdsale.sol"&gt;PreSaleWithCapCrowdsale contract&lt;/a&gt;.
You will see that I preferred to be explicit about the conditions instead of
using &lt;code&gt;super&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_preValidatePurchase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_beneficiary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;uint256&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_weiAmount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;internal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_beneficiary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_weiAmount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;timestamp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;openingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;||&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;whitelist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_beneficiary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;timestamp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;closingTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;weiRaised&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_weiAmount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to join me on these experiments, to try different combinations
of crowdsales and to play switching the order of the inheritance graph. We will
learn more about the resulting code that Solidity compiles, we will improve our
mental picture of the execution stack, and we will practice writing tests
that fully cover all the possible paths. If you have questions, find
errors on the implementations in OpenZeppelin, or find an alternative
implementation that will make it easier to develop crowdsales on top of our
contracts, please
&lt;a href="https://slack.openzeppelin.org/"&gt;let us know by sending a message to the slack channel&lt;/a&gt;.
I am &lt;em&gt;elopio&lt;/em&gt; in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A relevant experiment here is to use
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composition_over_inheritance#Benefits"&gt;composition over inheritance&lt;/a&gt;.
In OpenZeppelin we couldn't implement an architecture based on composition
because of the high gas costs implied, especially during deployment. That is
one of the reasons we are now hard at work
on &lt;a href="https://zeppelinos.org/"&gt;zeppelin_os&lt;/a&gt;, which minimizes deployment costs
by helping you use libraries that are already on-chain. Expect exciting news
very soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot to &lt;a href="https://github.com/ajsantander"&gt;Ale&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fiiiu"&gt;Alejo&lt;/a&gt;, who worked on these new contracts and helped
me to understand them. &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://elopio.net/es/blog/crowdsales-and-multiple-inheritance/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 15:58:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>